<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-11-11T10:12:47-07:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">What Can We Code Today?</title><subtitle>A coding blog by Cory Bergquist</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Kiwifruit</title><link href="/2018/08/22/kiwifruit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kiwifruit" /><published>2018-08-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-08-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2018/08/22/kiwifruit</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/08/22/kiwifruit.html">&lt;p&gt;Kiwifruit (often abbreviated as kiwi), or Chinese gooseberry is the edible
berry of several species of woody vines in the genus Actinidia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common cultivar group of kiwifruit is oval, about the size of a large
hen’s egg (5–8 cm (2.0–3.1 in) in length and 4.5–5.5 cm (1.8–2.2 in) in
diameter). It has a fibrous, dull greenish-brown skin and bright green or
golden flesh with rows of tiny, black, edible seeds. The fruit has a soft
texture, with a sweet and unique flavor.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ted</name></author><summary type="html">Kiwifruit (often abbreviated as kiwi), or Chinese gooseberry is the edible berry of several species of woody vines in the genus Actinidia.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Apples</title><link href="/2018/08/21/apples.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apples" /><published>2018-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2018/08/21/apples</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/08/21/apples.html">&lt;p&gt;An apple is a sweet, edible fruit produced by an apple tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple trees are cultivated worldwide, and are the most widely grown species in
the genus Malus. The tree originated in Central Asia, where its wild ancestor,
Malus sieversii, is still found today. Apples have been grown for thousands of
years in Asia and Europe, and were brought to North America by European
colonists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jill</name></author><summary type="html">An apple is a sweet, edible fruit produced by an apple tree.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Got Into Web Development</title><link href="/2018/05/26/why-got-into-web-development.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Got Into Web Development" /><published>2018-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2018/05/26/why-got-into-web-development</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/05/26/why-got-into-web-development.html">&lt;h1&gt; Why I got into web development. &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; A barista who wants to switch from coffee to code. &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been looking for a career change for quite some time. I have been a barista for five years, and while I enjoy the fast pace environment, the awesome co-workers, and a pretty flexible schedule, I’m ready for to switch to something that can really put my mind to use. As luck would have it, I stumbled on the idea of learning to code while talking with my sister about potential job changes. I’ve always been interested in figuring out what makes things tick, and as it turns out, there’s quite a bit of ticking that goes on behind the scenes of the websites we visit on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out to find as much free information about coding as I could, which was enough to keep me busy for several years if I wanted! After spending about a month completing a few different free courses that focused on Ruby, I realized that this could be a real passion of mine, and I decided that I could use a little guidance in my journey and signed up for Flatiron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after only learning the basics, I found that I could sit down and really focus on the problem solving aspects of trying to get a particular chunk of code to work. Even if my code wasn’t the prettiest, I could understand enough to see why something wasn’t working. As I spend more time, and dive into more complex code, I find that I can start thinking a little less about the language aspect, and really hone in on my problem solving skills. The more I learn the tools, the more I feel like I can accomplish!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that I didn’t expect to feel, was a genuine interest in solving other people’s problems. When I first began researching about coding, I mostly focused on how I might use this information to create things for myself, but after spending a decent amount of time solving labs, I get a sincere sense of pride when I’m able to spot the issue, and problem solve my way into a block of code that functions properly. With this mindset, I feel like I will be able to happily jump into any company and work through any coding issues they might have.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cory Bergquist</name></author><summary type="html">Why I got into web development. A barista who wants to switch from coffee to code.</summary></entry></feed>